Finding Aid for Hull Family Papers, 1869-1984
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Hull Family Papers, 1869-1984 1869-1960
Hull family.
1 phonograph records
3 oversize volumes
4 linear feet
91437 Aa 2
Letterbook (1869-1872) of George Hull, Livingston County, Michigan, farmer and businessman, relating to his grocery business, and letters (1888-1899) to his son Lawrence then attending Lawrenceville School in New Jersey relating to the family's fruit farm at Pleasant Lake; papers of Lawrence's wife, Eliza Darling Hull, student at the University of Michigan; papers of Lawrence and Eliza's son Leroy relating to World War I service; papers of Lawrence and Eliza's daughter Isabelle MacFarlane Hull; diaries of Leroy's wife, Frances Ball Hull, 1915-1919 and 1947-1957; papers of Leroy and Frances's son George M. Hull; papers of Leroy and Frances's daughter Jean Hull Ruhman; photographs; and scrapbooks.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Jean Hull Ruhman and Mr. John Ruhman (donor no. 7826 ) in July 1990, and Ann Ruhman (donor no. 7826 ) in November 2009.
The collection is open to research.
The Hull family has been prominent in Michigan's Washtenaw, Livingston, and Wayne Counties since the first representatives of the family arrived in the state in 1833. George Hull (1827-1912) and his wife Isabelle were farmers. They owned their first farm in Saline, farmed in Hamburg Township from 1870 to 1883, and spent their final years working a fruit farm at Pleasant Lake in Livingston County. Their son, Lawrence C. Hull (1857-1916), attended school in Lawrenceville, New Jersey. He became a well-known school administrator at the Lawrenceville School and later at the Michigan Military Academy. Lawrence's wife, Eliza Darling Hull, attended the University of Michigan from 1878 to 1882.
Lawrence and Eliza Hull's son, Leroy Wetmore Hull (1888-1972) became a prominent Detroit area physician. A graduate of the University of Michigan Medical School Class of 1911, Leroy served in World War I and later became president of the Wayne County Medical Society, the Detroit Academy of Medicine, the Michigan State Medical Society, and the American Urological Association. His wife, Frances E. Ball Hull (1896-1987) was active in community affairs.
Leroy and Frances Hull's son George M. Hull served in the United States Army during World War II, and subsequently attend Kenyon College in Gambier, Ohio. He returned to Michigan, and became a stockbroker. He never married. Their daughter, Jean Hull Ruhman, attended Wells College and Wayne State University, and became an elementary school teacher in the Detroit area. During the late 1950s she taught in Japan and Northern Africa (Tripoli) for the American Dependent Schools. While teaching abroad, she met and married Bryan Ruhman; they had two children, Anne and John.
A family tree of the Hull Family as well as further biographical information can be found in the first folder of the collection.
The Hull Family Papers consists of nine series: Family Materials, George L. Hull and Isabelle M. Hull, Lawrence C. Hull and Eliza Darling Hull, Isabelle MacFarlane Hull, Dr. Leroy Hull and Frances Ball Hull, George M. Hull, Jean Hull Ruhman, Audio-Visual Materials, and Scrapbooks. The collection contains letters, diaries, photos, clippings, and ephemera. The strength of the collection lies in its documentation of life in nineteenth-century southern Michigan, the World War I correspondence of Dr. Leroy Hull, the World War II correspondence of George M. Hull, and the 1950s travel correspondence and photographs of Jean Hull Ruhman.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Michigan--Livingston County.; Fruit.; Hamburg (Mich.: Township); Hull, Eliza Darling.; Hull family.; Hull, Frances Ball.; Hull, George L.; Hull, George M.; Hull, Isabelle MacFarlane.; Hull, Lawrence Cameron, d. 1916.; Hull, Leroy.; Lawrenceville School.; Livingston County (Mich.); Orchards.; Physicians--Michigan--Wayne County.; Pleasant Lake (Livingston County, Mich.); Ruhman, Jean Hull.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; World War, 1914-1918.; Physicians' spouses--Michigan--Wayne County.; Teaching.; Travel--Japan.; Travel--Libya.; World War, 1939-1945--Personal narratives, American.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Hull family.; Vietnam.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Family materials
  The Family Materials series contains a family tree and photocopied biographical information relating to the Hull family and their history in Michigan.
  - Biographies and family tree (Box 1)
- George L. Hull and Isabelle M. Hull
  The George L. Hull and Isabelle M. Hull series consists largely of the letterbook (1869-1872) of the Hull, Robinson, and Company grocery business and correspondence from 1888-1899, primarily from George Hull to his son, Lawrence, who was then away at school in Lawrenceville, New Jersey. The letters give some insights into life on the Hull family farm at Pleasant Lake. There is also an early photo of George and Isabelle.
  - Photo and obituary (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1888, 1894-1899 (Box 1)
  - Hull, Robinson, & Company Letterbook, 1869-1872 (Box 1)
- Lawrence C. Hull and Eliza Darling Hull
  - Lawrence C. Hull
    The second series, Lawrence C. Hull and Eliza Darling Hull includes a family photo, a few personal papers, and materials from his tenure at the Michigan Military Academy. Lawrence Hull's wife, Eliza Darling Hull, attended the University of Michigan and several of her student papers from both her high school days in LaPorte, Indiana and UM are included (1873-1882). These are well-written essays on a variety of subjects, including one on the plight of the American Indian and one on coeducation. Eliza's diary from 1896-1900 while her husband was at Lawrenceville School is also in the collection. There are also photographs of the movie The Varmint based on Owen Johnson's book The Varmint, which depicts life at the Lawrenceville School in the 1890s. The character of "The Old Roman" was based on Lawrence Hull, and Leo G. Carroll played the part of "The Old Roman" in the movie version. An autographed copy of the novel, belonging to Lawrence's daughter Isabelle can be found in the Isabelle MacFarlane Hull series.
    - Personal (photos) (Box 1)
    - Michigan Military Institute (Box 1)
    - Photos from movie, The Varmint (Box 1)
  - Eliza Darling Hull
    - Student papers, 1873-1882 (Box 1)
    - Diary, 1896-1900 (Box 1)
- Isabelle McFarlane Hull
  The Isabelle MacFarlane Hull series includes accounts of and documents relating to her travels, and a personal autographed copy of The Varmint. The book depicts life at the Lawrenceville School in the 1890s.
  - Travel accounts, 1923-1951 (sister of Dr. Leroy Hull), 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous travel documents, 1938-1951 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - The Varmint by Owen Johnson, 1910 (Box 1)
    (personal autographed copy of Isabelle McFarlane Hull)
- Dr. Leroy Hull and Frances Ball Hull
  The Dr. Leroy Hull and Frances Ball Hull series makes up a large part of the collection. There is one folder of photos including those of the U of M Medical School Class of 1911. There is also a folder of correspondence from Leroy, primarily to his sister Grace, regarding his service in World War I. Dr. Hull's professional activities are documented through photographs, clippings, bulletins, and other material generated by various professional societies. Also included are some photos from a medical tour Dr. Hull made to Vietnam in the 1960s. Dr. Hull's wife, Frances Ball Hull (1886-1987) was a member of Detroit Central High School's Class of 1915. Included in the collection are her high school yearbook, her diaries from 1915-19 and 1947-57, and several Yearbooks from volunteer associations of which she was a member.
  - Dr. Leroy Hull
    - All Saints Episcopal Church, Detroit, MI, 1934 1975 (Box 1)
    - Photos (Box 1)
    - World War I correspondence (Box 1)
    - Army Records, 1917 1919 (Box 1)
    - Professional activities-clippings (Box 1)
    - Professional activities (with photos) (Box 1)
    - Vietnam photos (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Frances Ball Hull
    - Detroit Central HS Class of 1915 (Box 2)
    - Diaries, 1915-1919, 1953-1955 (Box 2)
    - Volunteer Association Yearbooks, 1955-1963 (Box 2)
- George M. Hull
  The fifth series, George M. Hull, consists of correspondence written during his World War II Army service, miscellaneous correspondence, and materials relating to his education at Northern High School in Detroit, Kenyon College, Wayne State University, and Northern High School, and a scrapbook from his childhood.
  - Alpha Omega Fraternity, Northern High School, Detroit, Michigan 1917-1989 (Box 2)
  - Army Records, 1943-1945 (Box 2)
  - Autograph Book, 1937-1938 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1942-1979 undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Kenyon College and Wayne University materials, 1947-1950 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1930-1931 (Box 2)
  - Theater Programs, Northern High School, Detroit, Michigan, 1942 1944 (Box 2)
  - World War II Correspondence (from George M. Hull to his family)
    - September 28, 1942-September 15, 1943 (Box 2)
    - October 4, 1943-February 24, 1944 (Box 2)
    - March 21, 1944-August 5, 1944 (Box 2)
    - August 10, 1944-November 12, 1944 (Box 2)
    - December 2, 1944-January 12, 1945 (Box 2)
    - January 15, 1945-March 21, 1945 (Box 2)
    - March 23, 1945-August 25,1945 (Box 2)
    - September 6, 1945-December 1, 1945 (Box 2)
  - World War II Correspondence, 1943-1944 (to George M. Hull) (Box 2)
- Jean M. Hull Ruhman
  The Jean Hull Ruhman series consists of correspondence, documents related to her employment with the Department of the Army as a teacher in the American Dependent Schools, wedding invitations, travel memorabilia, and research papers and notes from her education at Wells College and Wayne State University.
  - American Dependent Schools Employment documents, 1953-1959, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence from Jean Hull, 1942-1957, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence to Jean Hull and family, 1943-1955 (scattered), and undated (Box 3)
  - Delta Alpha Delta, 1941-1943 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Travel Memorabilia, ca. 1950s (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1950-1955 (Box 3)
  - Research Papers and Notes, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Teaching materials, 1955-1959 (Box 3)
  - Wedding Invitations, 1947-1957 (Box 3)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  The Audio-Visual Materials series consists of photographs, negatives, slides, and one phonograph record. The photographs are arranged by family member, and topically where appropriate. The family photographs include candid snapshots of family members, family gatherings, and formal family portraits, while the travel photographs document Jean Hull Ruhman's European, Asian, and African travels. There are also photographs of one family member's house, miscellaneous, mostly unidentified negatives, several slides relating to Jean Hull Ruhman's family, and souvenir photographs from France, Canada, and the United States. A phonograph record containing early recordings of "The Yellow and the Blue," and "The Victor's March" is housed in the Phonograph Record Collection.
  - Photographs
    - Family Photographs
      - Eliza Darling Hull, Albums, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Charles E. Hull, Album, 1885 (Box 3)
      - Dr. Leroy Hull, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Frances Ball Hull (Box 3)
      - George M. Hull, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Jean Hull Ruhman and family
        - Christmas Photos, 1974 undated (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous Photos, undated, 3 folders (Box 3)
        - Unidentified Negatives, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous Identified (Box 4)
      - Unidentified (Box 4)
    - Travel Photographs (Jean Hull Ruhman)
      - Asia (Box 4)
      - California (Box 4)
      - Camp McGill, Japan, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Egypt, 1984 (Box 4)
      - Ireland, 1984 (Box 4)
      - Germany, Rhine Valley, 1984 (Box 4)
      - Switzerland, 1984 (Box 4)
      - Tripoli (Box 4)
      - Unidentified Locations (Box 4)
    - Houses (unidentified) (Box 4)
    - Slides, Jean Hull and family (Box 4)
    - Souvenir Travel Prints (Williamsburg, VA; France; and Ottawa, Canada) (Box 4)
  - Phonograph Record, "The Yellow and the Blue" (side A) and "The Victor's March" (side B), 1926 (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks
  The final series, Scrapbooks, consists of three Scrapbooks containing photographs, news clippings, and travel memorabilia. The final scrapbook relates to George M. Hull's involvement in the Alpha Omega Fraternity at Northern High School in Detroit.
  - Photographs and Correspondence, 1902-1954 (Volume 1)
  - Travel Memorabilia, 1939-1945 (Volume 2)
  - Alpha Omega Fraternity, Northern High School, Detroit, Michigan 1938-1941 (Volume 3)
Related Material
The Detroit Historical Museum has additional Hull family materials.